Preliminary Guide to the Thomas Rain Crowe Papers, 1965-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Thomas Rain Crowe Papers, 1965-2000, 32 Boxes
  - New Native Press Records (Box NNP 1)
    - Chapbooks (Box NNP 1)
      - Why I am a Monster, trans. Thomas Crowe (Box NNP 1)
      - You Must Go Home Again, Thomas Crowe (see also, Oversize series) (Box NNP 1)
      - The Snow Has No Voice, John Smelcer (Box NNP 1)
    - Drafts and Proofs (Box NNP 1)
      - Poems for Che Guevara's Dream (Box NNP 1)
      - Encyclopedia of Native American Tribes (Box NNP 1)
      - The Laugharne Poems (Box NNP 1)
      - In Wineseller's Street, Hafiz (Box NNP 1)
      - Night Sun (Box NNP 2)
        Includes materials for The Personified Street, New Native, and Water from the Moon.
      - Against Information production materials (Box NNP 2)
      - Writing the Wind (Box NNP 3)
        Includes correspondence, drafts and proofs, typesetting, and some corrections.
      - Writing the Wind (Box NNP 4)
        Includes manuscripts, notes, corrections, publicity, and reviews.
      - Writing the Wind (Box NNP 5)
        Includes corrections, designs, and other proof materials.
      - New Native Press letterhead, stationary, catalogs, etc. (Box NNP 5)
      - Seizures of the Sun (Box NNP 5)
        Includes correspondence, originals, manuscripts, proofs, laser-set texts, etc. Some materials removed to Oversize series.
      - Starfuck (Box NNP 5)
        Many files transferred to electronic records server. Also includes copies of extracts, drafts, etc.
      - Celtic Blood (Box NNP 5)
        Includes typeset proofs, typescript, and covers.
      - Celtic Blood (Box NNP 6)
        Includes correspondence, clippings, reviews, proofs.
    - Unpublished submissions (Box NNP 6)
    - Final publications (Box NNP 6)
      Includes Clouds; The Wake Up Man; Iris; The Book of Rocks; The Thief of Words; Over Population; Stories of the Seven-headed Sewing Machine; Deep Language; Two Lives; Poems for Che Guevara's Dream; Why I am a Monster; You Must Go Home Again (1979 and 1990); The Perfect Work; Against Information; Seizures of the Sun; The Laugharne Poems; In Wineseller's Street; Celtic Blood; Anthems of an Uncut Field; Kenneth Patchen: Rebel Poet in America; Writing the Wind; Night Sun; Starfuck: A Cybernovel (diskette removed to electronic records server).
    - Other publications: broadsides and layouts (Box NNP 6)
  - Fern Hill Records (Box FH 1)
    - The Sound of Light: recording information, 1991 and undated (Box FH 1)
    - Correspondence for Swimming with Her, 1995 and 1996 (Box FH 1)
    - The Laugharne Poems, 1995 (Box FH 1)
    - Richard Cambridge, The Marlboro Man Talks with God, 1994-1996 and undated (Box FH 1)
    - Against Information, 1994 (Box FH 2)
    - TRC and the Boatrockers (Box FH 2)
  - Publicity (Box Pub 1)
    - Thomas Rain Crowe archives and publicity (Box PUB 1)
    - New Native Press and Fern Hill (Box PUB 1)
      - Night Sun (2 folders) (Box PUB 1)
      - Danielle Truscott (2 folders) (Box PUB 1)
      - Against Information (2 folders) (Box PUB 1)
      - Writing the Wind (2 folders) (Box PUB 1)
      - Reviews of Crowe and NNP books (Box PUB 1)
      - Seizures of the Sun (2 folders) (Box PUB 1)
      - Welsh poets tour, 1997 April (Box PUB 1)
      - Mr. Mojo Risin' (2 folders) (Box PUB 1)
      - Picaza and Crowe promotional materials (Box PUB 1)
      - Bio-regional Magazine (Box PUB 2)
      - Mirrors of the Moon, 1992-1993 (Box PUB 2)
      - Metamora: The Eyes of the Butterfly (Box PUB 2)
      - Creative, organizational work, performances, teaching, etc. (Box PUB 2)
      - Jubilee, 1987 (Box PUB 2)
      - A Sense of Place, 1988 (Box PUB 2)
      - National Humanities faculty, 1984-1985 (Box PUB 2)
      - John Trudell Concert, 1996 (Asheville) (Box PUB 2)
      - Miscellaneous flyers, brochures, clippings (Box PUB 2)
      - May 1998 NC Reading tour (Box PUB 3)
      - Cincinnati/Cleveland readings, 1993 Oct. (Box PUB 3)
      - Asheville Poetry Festival, 1995 (Box PUB 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box PUB 3)
      - Asheville Poetry Review (Box PUB 3)
      - Writings and artwork by students at Macon County School District (NC) (Box PUB 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box PUB 3)
  - Clippings (8 folders) (Box PUB 3)
  - Photographs (Box PUB 3)
  - Audiovisual Materials (Box AV 1)
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    Includes CDs; cassettes of live performances, studio sessions, soundtracks, out takes, interviews; videos of performances, readings.
  - Oversize Materials (Box OVSZ 1-OVSZ 4)
    Oversize printed materials, including publications, broadsides, posters, production materials, and some artwork.
- Addition (2006-0075), 1991-2006, 55 Boxes
  Addition (2006-0075) (11,714 items; 32.8 lin. ft.; dated 1991-2006) comprises New Native Press published books, original drafts and manuscripts, recordings, posters, book cover art and proofs, and galleys. Includes material related to the publication of Zoro's Field; Red Lipstick; 10,000 Dawns; Drunk on the Wine of the Beloved; and The Baby Beat Generation; as well as substantial editorial office and general correspondence. There are also articles, interviews, reviews, color and black-and-white photographs, audio cassettes and CDs, video cassettes, as well as CD-Rs and 3.5" computer diskettes.
  CLOSED: This addition is closed to researchers.
- Addition (2008-0288), 2005-2008, (7 boxes)
  Addition (2008-0288) (7875 items; 10.5 lin. ft.; 2005-2008) includes book manuscripts, project files, articles, publications, interviews, newspaper clippings, and correspondence. Materials cover both Crowe's work and his interaction with other poets and organizations. Books include Why I am a Monster, Rare Birds, A House of Girls, and The End of Eden. There are also several CDs, a 3.5" floppy disk, an audio cassettes, and two DVDs.
  - NNP files (Box 1)
  - Rare Birds manuscripts and files
  - Miscellaneous files from friends and young poets (manuscripts, projects, articles, letters) (Box 2)
  - The Boatrockers files
  - Manuscript files (Box 3)
    - Why I am a Monster
    - The Book of Rocks
    - Radiogenesis
    - A House of Girls
    - The End of Eden
    - Rare Birds
  - Publications (Box 4)
    - Newspapers
    - Books
    - Magazines
    - Miscellaneous media on Thomas Rain Crowe
    - Recordings of Thomas Rain Crowe
    - Interviews with Thomas Rain Crowe
    - Audio CDs, (11 CDs)
  - Correspondence, 2006-2008 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous files (publications and projects) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 7)
  - Newspaper articles and clippings
  - DVDs:
    - Zoro's Field, A Walden for Today, 2007 (The Thoreau Society annual meeting)
    - Live at Lenoir-Rhyne College, 2004
    - "My Life in the Appalachian Woods," Heart of the High Country, show 406, 2007
    - "My Life in the Appalachian Woods: A Modern Day Walden," Zahner Conservation Lectures, 2007
- Addition (2011-0001), (7 boxes)
  Addition (2011-0001) (7.4 lin. ft.; 5550 items; dated 1987-2011) contains drafts and manuscripts from some of Crowe's books, including Crack Light, Rare Birds, The Watcher, and smaller amounts of material from A House of Girls, The End of Eden, Book of Rocks, The Brucciano Poems, Blue Rose of Venice, The Sacred Land, and Zoro's Field. Other writings represented include some of Crowe's published works, poems, and essays; articles; book reviews; and book blurbs written for other authors. Also includes correspondence with other writers, poets, and fans; coverage and correspondence regarding Crowe's involvement in several Tuckasegee environmental initiatives; materials from Crowe's band, Thomas Rain Crowe and The Boatrockers, including audio recordings of their spoken word poetry and music; clippings and fliers documenting Crowe's activities; photographs; and other miscellaneous material.
  Electronic media (floppy disks, CDs, and audio recordings) from this accession has been transferred to Duke's Electronic Records Archivist for preservation. Please contact Research Services with questions about this material.
  - Writings and Drafts of Books (Box 1)
    - A House of Girls, 2000
    - Rare Birds, 2008 and undated, (9 folders)
      Proofs, copies, pre-press copies, cover art, galleys, and photography credits.
    - The End of Eden, 2007-2009, (2 folders)
    - The Watcher, 2009-2010, (11 folders)
      Notes, letters, drafts and revisions.
    - The Watcher, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      Copyedits.
    - Book of Rocks, 2001-2009, (3 folders)
    - Crack Light, 2002-2011 and undated, (5 folders)
      Author's copy, corrected copies, and correspondence.
    - The Brucciano Poems, 2010
    - Blue Rose of Venice, 2007-2010
    - The Sacred Land, 2010
    - Hugh Alain Dal's Monster, 2005 and undated
    - Hugh Alain Dal's The Dead Lips Dance, 2006-2009 and undated, (2 folders)
    - Zoro's Field and University of Georgia Press, 2006-2009
  - Other writings, 2004-2011, (30 folders)
    Poems, essays, articles, interviews, book reviews, and book blurbs.
  - Published poetry, 2009-2010 (Box 3)
    Journals, anthologies, poetry reviews.
  - Fliers, other mentions of Thomas Rain Crowe, 2008-2010, (2 folders)
  - Thomas Rain Crowe and The Boatrockers, 1990-2000, (6 folders)
    Playlists, poems, notes, etc. 21 CDs and 2 cassette tapes were removed from the collection and transferred to Box 7, which is in the custody of the Electronic Records Archivist.
  - New Native Press possible books, 2000-2009, (6 folders)
  - Cross Cowee Mountain (New Native Press), 2008-2009
  - Anthology of Young French Poets manuscripts (abandoned New Native Press project), undated, (3 folders)
    3 CDs were removed from the collection and transferred to the Electronic Records Archivist.
  - Correspondence
    - Betsy Grubb, 2003-2004
    - Poet friends, 2009-2010
    - Keith Flynn, 2009-2010
    - Joe Napora, 2009-2010
    - Bobi Jones, 2010
    - Charles and Katherine Frazier, 2009-2010
    - Wayne Caldwell, 2009-2010
    - Janisse Ray, 2009-2010
    - John Lame, 2009-2010
    - Joy Harjo, 2008
    - Richard Lewis, 2009-2010
    - With young writers, 2006-2010, (3 folders)
    - With Beats/Baby Beats, 2005-2011, (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 2008-2010, (7 folders)
  - Miscellaneous photographs
  - Nametags from various events
  - Environmental activism and activities
    Materials from Crowe's community and environmental activism in his hometown of Tuckasegee, North Carolina.
    - Headwriters Conference, 2009
    - Walden Pond/Woods Project, 2006
    - Bioregionalism, 1987-2009
    - Rock quarry/Carolina Boulder and Stone/DENR, 2006-2007, (4 folders)
    - Rock quarry/Carolina Boulder and Stone/DENR, 2006-2007, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Save Our Mountains, (2 folders)
    - Historic Preservation District (Box 6)
    - Legasus/River Rock, (2 folders)
    - Press coverage of Crowe
  - Audio CDs and tapes (Box 7)
    RESTRICTED for electronic preservation purposes. Contact the Electronic Records Archivist with questions.
- Addition (2013-0032) 1978-2013, (3 boxes)
  Addition (2013-0032) (2700 items; 4.5 lin. ft.; 1978-2013) contains personal and professional correspondence including items relating to New Native Press and Tuckasegee, NC activism. Addition also includes copies and drafts of Crowe's manuscripts, miscellaneous publications and publicity materials, and New Native Press project drafts including broadsides. Additionally there are audio and video recordings from Black Mountain College Museum and Arts Center events and one CD of photographs.
  Box 3 is restricted because it contains audiovisual materials; these are closed until use copies can be made.
  - Miscellaneous publications, memorabilia, photocopies, and PR (Box 1)
  - Books, magazine articles, miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Jeff Davis (Box 1)
    - Keith Flynn (Box 1)
    - Christopher Martin (Box 1)
    - Joe Napora (Box 1)
    - John Lane (Box 1)
    - Marcio Simeos (Box 1)
    - Neeli Cherkovski (Box 1)
    - Caleb Beissert (Box 1)
    - Jack Hirschman (Box 1)
    - Richard Cambridge, Richard Lewis, and Carolyn Toben (Box 1)
    - Lisa Ezzard (Box 1)
    - Philip Daughtry (Box 1)
    - Wayne Caldwell (Box 1)
    - Sarah Menefee (Box 1)
    - Alessandra Bava (Box 1)
    - Anne Valley-Fox (Box 1)
    - Bobi Jones and Dewi Stephen-Jones (Box 1)
    - Various well-known writers (Box 1)
    - High school friends and girlfriends (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2000-2013 and undated, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous magazine articles, calendars, and memorabilia (Box 2)
  - Manuscript drafts and correspondence
    - Beautiful by Caleb Beissert, 2013 (Box 2)
    - The Wake Up Man by Thomas Rain Crowe, 2011 (Box 2)
    - Essential Occupation by Steve Brooks, 2012 (Box 2)
    - From the Middle Woods by Neeli Cherkovski, 2011 (Box 2)
    - Voices from the American Land (Box 2)
    - Crack Light by Thomas Rain Crowe, 2011 (Box 2)
    - A House of Girls by Thomas Rain Crow, French translation (Box 2)
    - A Conference of Birds by Christopher Martin, 2012 (Box 2)
  - Forwards, reviews, essays, projects, and interviews
    - C. Frazier's Nightwoods reviews and letter to the editor action et. al., 2011 (Box 2)
    - Book endorsements and cover blurbs, 2011 (Box 2)
    - North Carolina poet laureate position, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Tools' essay in Drafthorse, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Thomas Rain Crowe and Charles Frazier at UNCA, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Bigfoot War by Eric S. Brown book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Nightwoods by Charles Frazier book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Waking by Ron Rash book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Thomas Rain Crowe and Michael Revere letter to the editor, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Black Earth Institute (Box 2)
    - Flycatcher magazine, 2011 (Box 2)
    - The New Appalachia at The Mountain heritage Center, 2011 (Box 2)
    - Artist as Activist, 2010 (Box 2)
    - Recovering a Sense of the Sacred by Carolyn Toben (Box 2)
    - Gwarlingo, 2013 (Box 2)
    - Caleb's translations etc. / young writers et. al. suggested edits by Thomas Rain Crowe (Box 2)
    - A Land More Kind Than Home opinion, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Essay for Jack A. Hirschman biography for Alessandra Bava, 2012 (Box 2)
    - The Hills Remember book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Trieste Caffe piece with photos for Neeli's book (Box 2)
    - The Cove by Ron Rash book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Rose McLarney book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Dreamweed book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Conversations with Thomas Berry book review, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Tuckasegee Post Office case, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Eno Press book, 2011/2012 (Box 2)
    - G. Ellison's Nature Writers of WNC Anthology Volume II, 2009/2010 (Box 2)
    - Indie magazine interview, 2011 (Box 2)
    - Laurie Anderson in AVL (Box 2)
    - Sacred Sites book review, 2011 (Box 2)
    - Poet as Professional project, 2011 (Box 2)
    - Adirondack Review interview, 2011 (Box 2)
    - Thomas Rain Crowe and Eugene Friesen concerts, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Sallie Lee Sustaining Collaboration (Box 2)
  - New Native Press projects
    - Newspaper articles by and about Thomas Rain Crowe and New Native Press (Box 3)
    - Ned Mudd's Ji Bo book, 2012 (Box 3)
    - The Thief of Words (Box 3)
    - Over Population (Box 3)
    - Over Radiation (Box 3)
    - Stationary layouts (Box 3)
    - Website (Box 3)
    - Print-on-demand, digital books (Box 3)
    - Peace Will Come, 2012 (Box 3)
    - Newgrange (Box 3)
    - Lighthouse (Box 3)
    - Lyon in the Snow (Box 3)
    - Noetic Issues by Jeff Davis, 2005 (Box 3)
    - Favorite poems of childhood (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous broadsides (Box 3)
    - Ode to Wainio by Philip Daughtry (Box 3)
    - New Native Press 2006 catalog (Box 3)
    - The Big Dance, 2005 (Box 3)
    - If by Ted Pope, 2005 (Box 3)
    - The Idiot's Wind, 2005 (Box 3)
    - May It Continue (Box 3)
    - Achtung!, 2003 (Box 3)
    - The Perfect Work (Box 3)
    - How Long? by Ted Pope (Box 3)
    - I Wash Your Dishes, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Tuzas Journey by Michael Davitt, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Canticle by Richard Cambridge, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Starfuck by Ken Wainio (Box 3)
    - Body Poems by John Lane (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Black Mountain College readings, 2004-2005 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 3)
  - Printed Materials
    - Nightwoods by Charles Frazier, 2011 (Box 3)
    - Spirituality by Roger S. Gottlieb, 2013 (Box 3)
    - The Broad River Review Volume 44, 2012 (Box 3)
    - Asheville Poetry Review Volume 18, issue 21, 2011 (Box 3)
    - The Broad River Review Volume 43, 2011 (Box 3)
    - The Gallows Lord by Virginia L. Rudder, 1978 (Box 3)
    - The Devil's Millhopper Volume 8, number 1, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Nettles by Betty Adcock, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Dancing on Canaan's Ruins by Jim Clark, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Quicksilver 1 (Box 3)
    - The Man Who Grew Silent by Jim Peterson, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Shifting for Myself by Charlie Hughes, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Judy Hogan booklet in Russian, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous items removed from printed materials (Box 3)
  - Audiovisual Materials
    - BMCMAC "Beats to Black Mountain" reading Asheville, Spring 2005, (3 videocassette tapes) (Box 3)
    - Charles Frazier and Thomas Rain Crowe, (1 DVR disc) (Box 3)
    - BMCMAC A Beat Evening, 2005, (4 audio CDs) (Box 3)
    - BMCMAC From Beat to Black Mountain, 2005, (3 audio CDs) (Box 3)
    - BMCMAC A Beat Evening, 2004, (4 audio CDs) (Box 3)
  - Beat Photos, (1 CD, 10 files, 67.7 MB)
  - Oversize Materials (Opaperfolder 1)
    Oversize printed materials, including magazine articles and memorabilia.